"Why Do Most Users Quit GLP-1 Drugs Like Ozempic
(Semaglutide) Within Months?"
As the popularity
of Ozempic-type drugs,
like semaglutide, soars,
what do we need to know
about their effect
on our weight?
Even these newfangled
anti-obesity medications
aren’t a magic bullet.
The overall weight-loss benefits
are notable,
but nonetheless limited.
The best of them can produce
a 20 to 25 percent weight loss,
but they still leave most users
overweight or obese,
only modestly less so,
and, thus, still facing
major health risks.
And, of course,
the drugs are only effective
as long as they’re used.
Not only does
the weight loss plateau,
but years or, presumably,
a lifetime of continuing
treatment is required
just to maintain
their initial benefits,
and most people
stop taking them
within months before even
reaching an effective dose.
The manufacturers
recommend ramping up dosage
over four or five months,
but based on 169,000
real-world patients
using GLP-1 drugs
for weight management,
most individuals didn’t stay
on their prescribed treatment
for even three months,
which suggests
it was unlikely
they were achieving clinically
meaningful weight loss.
In fact, only about half take
the drug for even two months,
and 80 percent quit
by six months.
Why don’t people stick with it?
One reason may be
that these drugs are costly.
And costly is a bit
of an understatement.
The costs of these drugs
are enormous,
like $1,000 a month
in perpetuity,
since any lost pounds
can pile back on
if you stop taking them.
Wegovy, the high-dose Ozempic
used for weight loss,
costs up to about
$1,350 dollars a month.
So, that’s like paying $15,000
out-of-pocket every year.
And some say healthy eating
is expensive?
You could have Food Is Medicine
programs deliver healthy food
to your door for ten times less.
You could even have
fully prepared meals
delivered to your door
at a fraction of the cost
of the drug.
Of course, the drugs
should get cheaper.
There are hopes that competition
will lower prices,
but each GLP-1 drug is protected
by approximately 20 patents,
many up to 2040 or beyond;
so, they probably won’t get
much cheaper anytime soon.
But isn’t obesity itself
expensive?
Even factoring in
health benefits
and discounted prices,
these drugs
may not be cost effective.
In one analysis,
total annual health care costs
doubled for patients,
going from about $13,000
per year
before starting the drug
to $26,000 after.
Now, the benefits of weight loss
accrue over time,
but because lost pounds
are commonly regained
after stopping the drug,
an additional vexing conundrum
is created for payers
like insurance companies.
Why shell out all that money
to get people the drug,
if most are just
gonna stop taking it
and simply regain the weight?
Why are the drugs so expensive?
"There is no rational reason,
other than greed,"
according to Senator Sanders,
noting that Canadians
and Germans
are paying about 10 times less
for the same drugs.
Wegovy, the high-dose Ozempic
used for weight loss,
can sell for $1,300 a month
in the U.S.
but less than a hundred
a month in the U.K.
Here’s what
different countries pay
for the exact same dose
of Ozempic.
The researchers even calculated
the "estimated minimum price,"
how much it could
be manufactured
and sold profitably for.
So, for 40 dollars a month,
Novo Nordisk,
the makers of Ozempic,
could be pulling in
a 10 percent profit margin.
But why make 10 percent profit
when you can make
more than 3,000% profit?
But don’t they need
those huge profit margins
to recoup research
and development?
I mean, it’s expensive
to develop drugs.
Novo Nordisk spends
twice as much money
enriching its shareholders,
by doing things
like stock buybacks
to jack up stock prices,
than it does on all R&D.
In fact,
most big drug companies
spend more on these
kind of self-enrichment schemes
than actual research.
Whatever the actual cost
of developing a drug,
drug companies may spend
far more on marketing drugs
than developing them.
For example, while gouging
patients $1,000 a month
for their drugs,
Novo Nordisk was spending
millions of dollars
wining and dining doctors
to prescribe more of them.
Hundreds of thousands
of meals and snacks
served to promote drugs
like Ozempic.
In fact, Novo Nordisk
was actually suspended
from a pharmaceutical industry
trade association
for failing to disclose
its sponsorship
of a training course
for healthcare professionals
that just so happened
to plug one of its GLP-1 drugs,
a violation bad enough
for the Royal College
of Physicians
to sever its ties
with the drug giant.
Anyway, back to
the original question:
Why do so few people
stay on these drugs?
Well, people may start out
obese and end up obese.
Is it worth paying $1,000
a month just to stay less obese?
You can see why people
might just cut their losses.
But no, the study showed that
most people who quit these drugs
after just a few months
were not only insured,
they had their drugs
covered by their insurance.
So, maybe the reason
most people quit
so soon after starting
is not due to their cost,
but rather their side effects,
which we’ll cover next.